hello and welcome everyone it's active
inference guest stream number 48.1 on
July 19 2023
we're here with Arthur Giuliani and Adam
saffron also joined by Michael Edward
Johnson in discussion we're going to
have a presentation and then a
conversation about deep canals a deep
learning approach to refining the
canalization theory of Psychopathology
so thank you all for joining and looking
forward to this presentation and
discussion
thanks Daniel I'm very happy to be here
uh with admin Mike to talk about this
work and to discuss more broadly
um this General Direction that's emerged
over the past few years to try to
utilize some of the concepts from the
active inference World
um and computational modeling more
generally to understand what's going on
both in Psychopathology and in
psychedelic therapy uh yeah so I'll give
a brief a presentation and we'll move
into a kind of more General discussion
of this work
it'll start uh with some kind of General
considerations around psychedelic
therapy some of the Neuroscience of
psychedelics
um and then move kind of more
specifically into the model
so there is this class of drugs the
serotonergic Psychedelic drugs which
include psilocybin DMT LSD and others
and the past decade has seen a
Resurgence of interest in psychedelic
therapy psychedelic assisted
Psychotherapy
um where one or multiple of these drugs
is used in conjunction with a kind of
psycho therapeutic protocol
um and there's been a lot of investment
of money and time and clinical resources
into utilizing these drugs for
treatments depression anxiety disorders
substance use disorders and others
and there seems to be quite a lot of
um
positive signals suggesting that these
kinds of therapeutic interventions can
actually be uh quite effective
um so there's a number of studies
suggesting that
psilocybin assisted Psychotherapy can be
helpful for depression anxiety substance
use disorder and others
um and as this work advances
um they're more and more larger clinical
trials comparing it for example to uh
the standard treatments with ssris
with multiple studies suggesting that
psilocybin assisted Psychotherapy is at
least as effective as
the Lexapro kind of didn't care
all of this seems to suggest and the
timelines are kind of pointing at this
idea that
psilocybin treatment for major
depressive disorder maybe only a couple
of years away
um from becoming uh
approved as natural treatment in the
United States which
means that it's quite important for us
to understand what's going on
mechanistically in the brain so that
these kinds of treatments can be best
optimized best determines how to be used
um
yeah
or which kinds of
mental issues people might be having and
under what
kinds of treatment protocols we might
expect the most success I think
this will also ultimately hopefully lead
to the development of even better drugs
even better treatment protocols
um and much more personalized okay
so some of the basics of how these drugs
work on the brain for those who are
unfamiliar right so they're these are
the serous synergic psychedelics they
are search energy because they act as
agonists for a number of Serotonin
receptors in the brain and the central
nervous system more broadly
um it's thought that most specifically
uh these drugs like psilocybin work
through agonizing the serotonin
5-ht2a receptor
um
and this has been
demonstrated multiple times by using
blockers
antagonists of the 5ht2a receptor which
seemed to largely remove the effect of
psilocybin or other psychedelic drugs
and what this 2A receptor does when it's
agonized is it
excites the neuron making it more likely
to Fire and this is kind of essential to
some of the downstream effects
so given that
um it seems that this this 2A receptor
that psychedelics are mainly targeting
the question then become the school
where in the brain or these two a
receptors most widely expressed
and research has focused on I would say
three kind of key areas over the past
decade or so the first being the
thalamus which is a region involved in
the gating of sensory information into
the cortex there's a lot of expression
in the cortex itself
expression for example in the visual
system
which is perhaps not surprising given
the prevalence of visual hallucinations
and Technology use but therapeutically a
lot of focus has been on the prefrontal
cortex where there is also a dense
expression of these receptors and then
also more recent work has looked at the
claustrum which is a small brain region
responsible for coordinating the
transition dynamics of cortical
activation
and this too is likely of essential
importance to the Psychedelic effect
so kind of moving up one level of
abstraction to fmri studies there are a
few kind of like key takeaways
um which have I been identified from a
few different uh fmri studies looking at
um psychedelic use
um kind of the main theme has largely
been this idea of increased entropy or
increased complexity of the cortical
activation in the brain
um so there are various measures of this
um on the right here there's a figure of
one of the common measures of complexity
and
looking at various different kinds of
states that an individual might be in
and how that relates to complexity right
so you have individuals like vegetative
States
um or anesthetized anesthetized States
having relatively low brain activity
complexity you have individuals in awake
States like higher complexity and then
individuals who who have ingested either
psilocybin or LSD I'm showing the
highest brain complexity
now along with this uh rather than just
this kind of like single unified score
there's work looking particularly at the
changes in functional connectivity
between different brain regions or
different brain networks
um and the general Trend uh seems to be
that you have decreased within Network
functional connectivity and increase
between Network functional connectivity
right which this kind of can be
interpreted as different uh brain
networks which typically don't
communicate as much with each other more
likely to communicate with each other
ones you the effects of psychedelics
um
and the kind of like internal coherence
of networks uh is reduced under
psychedelics
um
people have maybe heard of this default
mode Network right which is responsible
for a lot of self-referential processing
which is responsible which is typically
activated for example when individuals
are off task
mind-wandering not like actively engaged
um the default mode network has been
kind of like consistently implicated in
being having less of this kind of like
within network connectivity less of this
functional integration
um and this has been hypothesized to be
one of the kind of key mechanisms of
the therapeutic effect of psychotics
in addition to looking at kind of like
brain network activity on a high level
uh you can then also zoom in much more
deeply and look at what's actually going
on
um at the neuron by neuron level or the
neuron connectivity level
um
here we see kind of very certain very
consistent
um story around this uh
psychoplastogenic effect to this
neuropathogenic effect where there are a
number of different markers of increased
plasticity in the brain so one that's
very common is this increased uh brain
derived neurotropic Factor
which we see hours after psychedelic use
um
for a variety of different uh
psychedelic drugs and this is then
accompanied a few hours later by visible
increases in the dendritic spine growth
in cortical pyramidal neurons so this is
both the number of dendritic spines and
the complexity of the spines so you can
see a very clear example of this here on
the right
where you have on the top the vehicle
and then the bottom to DMT treated uh
pyramidal neuron and the difference is
very very Stark you don't even have to
do any sort of um
actual computational analysis for it to
be clear that there's um quite
significant dendritic growth from a
single dosing
and the changes to functional
connectivity which I mentioned in the
previous slide
um tend to persist though in a less
extreme form than what we see during the
IQ effects
so the question then becomes given all
of this how can we attempt to tell a
consistent computational story what's
actually going on during both the acute
facts the post-acute effects and in
terms of the actual Downstream
therapeutic outcomes
so what's kind of been proposed
um as uh the one of the leading models
of this is the relaxed belief under
psychedelics model on the Rebus model of
Carhartt Harrison
um and so this Builds on the kind of
like active inference hierarchical
prediction processing uh framework where
we can understand the brain as the
series of predictors stacked kind of
like hierarchically along uh brain
Networks
um and
predictions are being made by higher
level Networks
um that are attempting to
uh predicts the errors of lower level
Networks
um
and the process of basically doing this
then produces this series of belief
Landscapes at different levels of spatio
temporal abstraction
um
and these belief Landscapes of course
can encode leaks with various levels of
precision
um and it's the modulation of this the
Precision of these beliefs which is
believed to take place under psychedelic
use
so here's kind of like a very high level
uh version of this three of this model
and how belief relaxation might actually
happen right so given that you have this
uh series of cortical networks which are
representing beliefs of different
spatial temporal scales we can
um kind of think of the thalamus as
being kind of like the entry point where
sensory information is being gated into
this hierarchical system and the
prefrontal cortex is being kind of like
one of the highest level networks right
which is then responsible for
um both representing the most abstract
kinds of beliefs as well as being kind
of the primary inhibiting force for all
of the downstream beliefs in the network
in the system
right so what is uh this had the agonism
of the 5ht2a receptor supposed to be
doing in this case
um well it's going to be decreasing the
prefrontal cortex's ability to make
coherence
um predictions and coherence
representations of belief which will
then disrupt its ability to inhibit
lower levels of the cortical hierarchy
at the same time by disrupt the this
activation of the
um salami or the destruction of Islamic
gating right is going to result in
additional sensory information entering
the cortex that wouldn't underwise onto
the cortex you have uh these kind of
disruptions at these two levels
um
which then results in uh beliefs being
uh spontaneously represented in ways
that they wouldn't normally be
represented and the Rebus model at least
um
is suggesting that this mainly is going
to manifest itself as a kind of
relaxation of these beliefs
so here is a kind of like very simple
diagram of what this might look like
um so you have some landscape of beliefs
here
and you can kind of interpret the
position along the uh the X and Y
or I'm going to see x and z believe in a
as being corresponding to some
particular belief that might be
represented by the network of this layer
or at this level of representation and
then the y-axis the height as being the
actual Precision of that belief right
um so here we have this kind of very
deep part on the right part of this
network or on this landscape and this
would be a very strongly represented
belief let's say
what the acute effects that psychedelics
have been understood to be doing right
is to be flattening the Sunscape to be
less strongly representing who strongly
represented beliefs to me making it
easier for the
um reversal of this landscape so to move
from uh one attractive state to another
attractive state
um
which is meant to be understood to be
kind of therapeutic in various ways
and then the post-acute effect being
some kind of return to normalcy but one
that is not totally complete one that
still incorporates some of these newly
relaxed beliefs these newly explored
beliefs
building on this Rebus model
um car and Harrison colleagues last year
proposed this canal model of
Psychopathology which basically kind of
takes the intuition that through
relaxation you know if the Revis model
is correct if the relaxation of beliefs
as a therapeutic outcome uh if you kind
of take that way of thinking to its
logical conclusion
um you might then uh propose something
like this which would say
um
if relaxing overly strong beliefs is
therapeutic then having overly strong
beliefs in the first place is
pathological in some kind of way
um and they refer to this uh
development to these overly strongly
represented beliefs as catalyzed beliefs
or and this problem generally is
canalization or this process of
developing them as analyzation and this
is the canal model of Psych pathology so
they kind of build on this idea uh this
you know set of previous work in the
literature suggesting that there may be
some primary factor of Psychopathology
and they suggest that this primary
factor is canalization
and in this work they discussed a number
of different
um psychopathologies which seem to quite
clearly fit this
um catalyzation type
um characterization so it's very
relatively straightforward I think to
understand things like addiction
depression anxiety disorders
obsessive-compulsive disorders all of
these involve in one way or another
having some strongly held beliefs
um typically negative negative beliefs
uh in the case of like depression
anxiety
um obsessive compulsive body image
disorder
um or in the case of you know substance
use disorder or some very strong beliefs
about what kind of behaviors should be
taken at any given time in any given
context
and then of course the effect of
psychedelics is to undo canalization
um and the better able any sort of
therapeutic intervention is to undue
canalization the more likely for a
positive therapeutic outcome
so I think this work has a lot of
strengths and there's a kind of Elegance
to it
um in our Canal's work that we had been
worked on
we kind of identify a couple of
limitations of this canal model and
attempt to extend and refine the model
in ways that I think ultimately make it
more powerful while kind of keeping the
the essential elegant Insight that
canalization is kind of like intimately
tied to like mythology
so the first kind of limitation I think
that we identify is that
um in the canal model it's very heavily
implied that all
uh forms of canalization are
pathological in one way or another
um and as I mentioned just now uh this
is clearly the case for a large Class A
very common psychopathologies
um it's when we start to look more
towards edge cases I think uh that these
exceptions start to problematize this
understanding right
um so if we consider Psychopathology is
such as bipolar borderline schizophrenia
depersonalization disorder
um
it becomes much more difficult to kind
of
easily classify these as simply problems
of overly strong priors in many cases
here we have problems of priors that are
not so strong or priors that seem to
drift over time in ways that are
problematic for both the individual and
uh the people that the individual are
close to
and if we think about psychedelics then
as being this kind of Panacea to undo
canalization and undo
um Psychopathology we also run into this
other issue which is that there are
certain kinds of psychopathologies which
are uh
typically uh
issues for use with psychedelics right
so schizophrenia being a very clear one
where there's evidence of psychedelic
use being a trigger for the onset of
psychosis and individuals who are
predisposed to schizophrenia
um there's also evidence of the
development of depersonalization
disorders with psychic with strong
psychedelic use
and this is not what we would expect if
psychedelics were simply
um
universally undoing uh
or getting rid of psychopathologies
there's also this idea which I think
Adam is going to develop quite a bit
later that
um
the stability of beliefs are is
typically correlated with positive
mental health outcomes not negative ones
and what is a stable belief if not one
that is highly penalized in some kind of
meaningful sense within within the
system
foreign
limitation is that
if you think about an actual dynamical
system one that uh
is parametrized in some kind of
meaningful way like a brain you know
which is parametrized by synaptic
connections and then instantiates uh
neural activity patterns over time and
we think about what kinds of
optimization Landscapes are actually
being induced by inside the system
uh we find that there's not just one
kind of catalyzation there's actually
two kinds of catalyzation
um and in our deep canals work we
attempt to kind of take inspiration from
Deep learning literature to tease apart
these two kinds of penalization and
understand them a bit more clearly
um
and they are just to kind of give a
a preview these two different things
overfitting in plasticity loss
um so overfitting is the problem uh
you have your catalyzed in a particular
kind of way and whatever sort of
policy you've learned whatever sort of
extent beliefs you have these don't
generalize to some other context during
context a
you may be very well adapted you move to
context B and whatever you've learned
doesn't apply there
then plasticity loss is a little bit
different
um elasticity loss has to do with one's
not one's ability to generalize for
other one's ability to adapt or to learn
so imagine you're in context a you may
or may not be well adapted to context a
if you move to context B the question
becomes are you able to adapt to contact
speed or not not are you immediately
already ready to deal with context B but
given time in context B can you learn
and change
and we use a very simple recurrent
neural network model to kind of make
sense of this
and I think this is important because
there can be different kinds of
canalization on these different kinds of
optimization Landscapes and these have
unique implications for the treatment of
psychopathology
and I think uh even more importantly
psychedelics work on these different
landscapes in different ways and so
understanding how they work uh is
essential to developing
better drugs better treatment protocols
and more personalized treatment
Okay so
what are these two optimization
Landscapes how can we make sense of them
this is kind of like the big overview
figure of the deep canals work
um
so we kind of start with this intuition
of our current neural network right and
in a recurrent neural network there are
these kind of twos there are these two
sets of parameters so you have at any
given time you have the actual weights
of the network
and then you have the hidden activation
of the network right and so the weights
of the network are data and the hidden
activation is H and there's some input
into the network at any given time step
um and then the output of the network is
a function of both the input and the
hidden State and the hidden state is
updated at every time the hidden
activation pattern
great and this gives us essentially
these two different Landscapes uh one
what we refer to as the inference
landscape or the type a landscape and
this is equivalent to the neural
activation pattern of a brain at any
time right so what gets read off from an
fmri what gets read off from the EEG is
going to correspond to this activity
landscape
but uh kind of like underlying or
supporting this activity landscape is
this other more fundamental landscape
which is the actual optimization
landscape that is induced by the
synaptic weights themselves
and this is what is the result of uh
right like synaptic connectivity in the
brain between all the sets of neurons in
the brain this is what is changing when
we have various forms of like heavy and
plasticity heavy and learning
um
and this is what kind of like
instantiates the possible sex of neural
activity patterns right so this is kind
of like a way we can start to understand
this
um
which is when we think about belief
Landscapes right as I mentioned before
you know here's a very simple diagram
where we have a two-dimensional belief
landscape and let's say there's uh you
know someone who's depressed or
potentially depressed and they might
have a negative self-image you know I'm
a terrible person I I can't do anything
right something like this this would be
encoded as a particular position in this
belief landscape
um you know where the neural activity
pattern looks like this this belief is
what gets expressed right
um
and there's another you know set of
neural activity patterns which would
correspond to a positive self-image and
positive self belief you know I'm great
I'm wonderful or even just I'm okay I'm
totally acceptable as a person
um and this would be a different set of
patterns
so uh based on the synaptic the actual
connectivity structure of the brain
right uh these two patterns May or be
maybe more or less likely so here these
are being represented by these uh two
different
um sets uh neural activation Landscapes
which are the result of two different
positions in the synaptic weight
landscape space and in this top space
um the one that's in the middle here
uh that then is represented here at the
top of uh part C of the figure we see
that there's very high Precision
assigned to or very high likelihood
assigned to the negative self-image
and very low likelihood here assigned to
the positive self-image
but in some other part of the uh
synaptic weight landscape a very
different kind of neural activity
landscape might be instantiated
um and this one kind of has the inverse
properties where negative self-image is
unlikely and positive self-image is much
more likely
um so we can kind of then understand
positions in the neural activity
landscape is kind of corresponding to
specific phenomenological experiential
instantiations of certain kinds of
beliefs right so like the actual
experience of
uh holding a negative supplement or
holding a positive self-image
and we can understand positions in the
synaptic weight landscape as being
something more General so in the case of
depression
um there might be a specific set of
synaptic weight connectivity which would
correspond to what you might call you
know a depressed individual someone who
might qualify as having a major
depressive disorder and another set of
synoptic weights connectivity pattern
that wouldn't qualify as that way
okay so before I get into this
psychedelic uh oh psychedelics relate to
this um I think Adam is going to talk a
little bit about
um some work he's done extending the
Rebus model
hello
so yeah I've been uh
thinking about this a while and then
along the way I met Arthur who also has
been thinking about this a while but in
different ways and so
um uh like Arthur's background isn't
um basically Consciousness science and a
very uh peculiar uh field of
computational Consciousness science in
terms of actual models of what it would
be to have a conscious system uh even
potentially an artificially conscious
system and so
um I'm coming from more free energy
principle and active inference my
background and Arthur's coming from more
mainstream machine learning and so we
we're coming together to explore uh this
beast from different perspectives and
been finding a lot of uh
I think very interesting overlaps
and so uh in terms of Albus the basic
idea is to take Rebus
um and expand on it we I love Rebus it's
a great framework
um and I'm I've been trying to make it I
guess more flexible in terms of being
able to handle like a wider range of
assumptions so not just talking about
relaxed beliefs but also potentially
strengthen beliefs in different
combinations
uh this was always part of the Rebus
framework and that you can have all
sorts of both direct and indirect
effects when you're dealing with a large
predictive hierarchy or any you know
complex system you change something in
one way but then you'll get an effect
elsewhere so if you have this hierarchy
of predictions for instance you can
potentially relax beliefs at higher
levels and that can indirectly cause
strength and beliefs at lower levels so
you can both get relaxed and strengthen
beliefs in psychedelics in all sorts of
different combinations
and so
um
with Albus the idea is um so I've been
calling uh as opposed to a belief
relaxation when you get this sort of
um basically a bottom right here you
might see it so this red would be
basically uh a something like a
synchronized complex of neural activity
um and potentially you've often
involving the thalamus which would be
thought to encode your predictions or
your top-down stream of priors which
then are suppressing the ascending
stream prediction errors
um and so under Rebus you're seeing here
uh relaxed predictions a smaller uh
complex of synchronized activity and the
gates are down just like Arthur
described more things are coming in
Rebus will sometimes be described in
terms of uh so when we're talking about
Rebus this idea of relaxing beliefs
we're thinking at the um functional or
computational level so like David Myers
and analyzing the mind you have these
three I suppose uh supervenient levels
out there compatible and synergistic so
computational functional
um like abstractly what is the system
doing uh something like the pseudocode
of the system and then implementational
mechanistically how's realized and then
in the middle some sort of algorithm
algorithmic intermediate abstraction
layer how are these computations
realized via these mechanisms some
bridging principle description
and so when it comes to Rebus
um you can adopt it in different ways
and relate to it differently so you can
relate to it at the functional level
um or you can relate to it at the
algorithmic or implementational levels
um in terms of where you're taking the
account so for instance uh you might
think something like Rebus effects is a
very valuable model of something like
what they call Quantum change with
psychedelics but you don't necessarily
believe in predictive processing but you
still might be you could say like a
Revis type theorist or you might be
thinking in terms of like Rebus like in
a more narrow sense of thinking of uh
predictive processing information flows
um but then when you get to like the
overall person and integrated organism
and the agent uh you might have
different interpretations there
um so with the work with Albus basically
the idea would be to take predictive
processing and to and models of
psychedelic action and suggest that
sometimes
um not only uh do we have these
relaxational belief Landscapes but we
might have the opposite of strengthening
and so specifically if you're activating
these five HD 2A neurons which would be
at the deeper levels of the cortical
sheet and also the deeper levels of the
cortical hierarchy more inwards and
higher up and these will be the Unice
Loop of the thalamus and thereby be able
to form large synchronous integrated
complexes
um but then when you excite them too
much they don't wait for each other to
sync up they fire or whenever they can
how to sink and this relaxes a belief
landscape however
it's not clear this should happen the
whole way through for any amount of
increasing the gain on these neurons So
in theory just increasing the gain a
little bit unless uh that might help
them to sync up that might strengthen
the belief whether it's a situationally
specific suggestion of you in this
context or maybe something old coming to
the surface and uh if you will
manifesting
um so Albus basically in a nutshell
would be saying
um to take Rebus and keep going with it
and look for different combinations of
both strengthened both directly and
indirectly strengthened and relaxed
beliefs
that's basically it and so I'm not going
to go into too many more details Arthur
and I just submitted this uh for
publication uh wish us luck hopefully
the reviewers will be useful
um maybe even kind but preferably useful
and um yeah I'll kick it back to Arthur
but before I do
um like this work uh
I think it's immensely important that we
get these details right these are
um extremely powerful medicines that
could revolutionize things or we could
have a backlash if we do it wrong if
we're careless if we
um don't see the risks but also if we're
overly beholden to like a single way of
viewing things prematurely we might also
miss opportunities to help
potentially enormous opportunities for
instance like you might not think of
helping people
um like look for instance micro dosing
for cognitive decline you might not have
thought of that
um and that might be a really big deal
that you do think of them so uh I guess
before going back to Arthur one more
thing would be just in terms of uh
at least for me like experientially like
the way I sometimes think of it as like
um with relation to well-being and uh
suffering
um
both things matter like the strength and
the strength of your positive beliefs
and the strength of your negative
beliefs and sometimes the negative
beliefs have positive aspects and vice
versa so it's it's both like you might
relax your beliefs and like after he's
like a Harry Potter metaphor like be
someone like out of it so much out of
the grip of the Dementors that usually
uh that under some circumstances might
be pursuing you that you have room to be
different to become different uh to
think different things under this
different state
um but additionally and not
um mutually exclusively not necessarily
in compatibly maybe synergistically the
strength of what beliefs you're able to
have in that moment and maybe draw upon
from the past could be deeply important
uh your values the kinds of beliefs that
you call upon in times of need and that
give you hope
um maybe those are just originally
suggested to you right there in the
session but maybe there's something else
another belief in that strengthening it
could be a good thing and even without a
clinical context like microdosers for
instance it's not clear they're exactly
they're trying to relax their beliefs
like the range of use cases the way we
want to relate them how we want to be in
the world
um
it seems complicated to me so I will
get back to Arthur
yeah thanks so much Adam
so with that context with all this uh I
want to talk a little bit about how we
might understand uh at a very high level
um
what psychedelics are doing to these two
uh Elite landscapes
so before I showed you very quickly I
guess I can go back to it
um in the Rebus model you know there's
only one type of optimization landscape
uh and so there's only one type of uh
canalization and what is you know
supposed to be happening is a relaxation
of beliefs
um which is strong during the acute
effect and persists in the post-acute
effect
so with uh Elvis though we might be able
to think about all of this a little bit
differently
um we can in during the acute effects of
psychedelics interpret what's happening
to the type a landscape as being less of
the kind of universal relaxation and
more of a kind of destabilization where
under certain circumstances beliefs are
being strengthened other beliefs are
being relaxed this is uh changing quite
rapidly over the course of time so you
know a certain belief may be
transiently strengthened a few minutes
later it may no longer be supported or
supportable
um
and this actually functionally you know
enables a kind of exploration of all the
POS of a wide space of belief
instantiations during the acute effects
of the drug
um
the uh as far as the inference landscape
is concerned you know post-acute effects
as Adam was saying it could be the fact
that certain positive beliefs are
explored and can be strengthened
um other negative beliefs might be
weakened this is kind of like the ideal
psychotherapeutic outcome
um
it may be you know on average if it's
something like a relaxation a general
relaxation of beliefs is uh what you
might see but the way that you get there
is likely going to be through a kind of
much more complicated process
I think what's that interesting and
related to also to what Adam said about
uh thinking much more broadly about how
psychedelics might be used in terms of
neurocognitive disorders in addition to
kind of like traditional
psychopathologies
um is to think about what's happening to
the the learning landscape the kind of
like underlying synaptic weight
landscape and what do we understand is
happening here kind of quite clearly is
there is uh neurogenesis
psychoplastogenic facts um there's
dendritic growth and what is this
enabling well this is enabling uh
greater connectivity between within and
in between networks
um
and so kind of from a functional uh
learning perspective learning theory
perspective what this means uh is that
gradient information can flow more
easily through these networks
um and what this means is that it's
easier to get from one part of the
network to the other part of the network
there are fewer of these kind of
optimization
uh local
um Minima there are fewer of these kind
of like tricky saddle points
um and what this means kind of like
functionally is that this plasticity
loss that I discussed earlier is going
to be less of an issue
and here it seems to be kind of like
regardless of the acute uh the actual
phenomenological effects uh you know
there are very strong Downstream effects
on uh this structural connectivity and I
think
um you know there's some interesting
work suggesting that there may actually
be independent mechanisms
um that are affecting these two
Landscapes so there's a reason we're
suggesting for example that uh
psychedelics as well as ketamine is able
to kind of like particularly bind to
receptors in the brain that produce that
are results in the kind of release of
the brain derived neurotropic factor and
then the downstream changes in synaptic
weighting and that this may be uh
potentially totally independent of the
5hc2a agonism right
um
and this has very interesting
implications for future drug design and
development
okay so I'm going to before my next
slide turn it over to Adam once more uh
to briefly talk a bit about
um
personality theory and the relationship
between uh psychedelics and personality
hello again
so um
so for the past few years I've been
doing some work with a personality
researcher Colin De Young
on intersections between the way agency
is modeled in the free energy principle
and active inference framework and the
way that persons are considered in
different situations and personality
science and looking for points of
intersection and so
um you know it's personally personality
is actually an extremely deep concept
and if you think of it it's
um I guess we call it like the normal
form of a system in terms of it's uh
what is the way you can describe the
most of the system
um with like the minimal message length
the
um account for the most with the least
and what we're trying to account for is
the states that people tend to occupy
people aren't always happy people aren't
always sad people aren't always you know
friendly they're not always angry it's
all sorts of things that are there
there's a range that people are
encountering but there's they tend to
occupy some states more than others and
you might call that the person their
personality and you might call that the
person many systems would have their own
Personalities in terms of trying to
describe uh something with their essence
and so uh they're attracting States
and so with uh Colin the Young's work
um he interprets personality and these
um major domains of Personality that
people have discovered uh a reliable
Factor structure ways you can Funk the
variance uh the big five as a trade
hierarchy but where these different
traits are interpreted as cybernetic
control parameters uh specifically
cybernetics in terms of the study of
goal seeking systems governed by various
forms of feedback that different stages
of uh the process of pursuing goals uh
evaluating outcomes updating
um that and you understanding that
basically the personality as different
modes of being in the world for
cybernetic systems interpreting them as
parameters for goal Pursuit because we
are goal seeking systems trying to
pursue the goals we value
um
and so
I guess moving to this the and with
relation we're talking about now both in
terms of Personality formation
reformation and the structure of
Personality
um
the piece so
okay to get to the P Factor uh
within personality theory this big five
traits the set of big five traits
there's a uh richer or more detailed uh
Factor structure
um a hierarchical uh structure for
personality that's been discovered
um so above the big five neuroticism
agreeableness conscientiousness
you'll have a metatrase of their shared
varias that's observed called stability
it's also been called Alpha by think
digmin
um and then above the traits of
extroversion and openness intellect you
have this metatrade of plasticity
and um are called beta and
the shared variance of these two
so what's interesting is that within uh
this field of
um within high top which is this effort
to try to characterize Psychopathology
using the same kind of data-driven
methods and personality science a
principled account of the structure of
Psychopathology the way that personality
has a structure you're trying to account
for this there seems to be a common
factor across many forms of
Psychopathology that's referred to as
the P factor and it tends to be the
inverse of stability it's high
neuroticism
uh low agreeableness and low
conscientiousness and this is actually
uh
uh what's referred to in the article
um as
um this P Factor
thinking of it as a lack of flexibility
you could make a case for it but more
straightforwardly it seems to be a lack
of stability for something to be a lack
of flexibility you would maybe be
thinking of something more like uh
plasticity like someone having low
plasticity but empirically that's not
what's observed and so empirically
that's not what's observed that's a very
important detail we should stop and take
note of so you might say that um rather
than emphasizing the first principle
component of Psychopathology it's
possible that this canal models is
actually focusing on the second Factor
um it's not you know it's not a contest
it's still enormously a big factor like
the work of Stephen Hayes and others
showing like a lack of flexibility is
trans diagnostic but just empirically
speaking the first principle component
of Psychopathology might be more closely
related to a lack of stability rather
than insufficient plasticity
yeah
um well I guess one more thing to think
of in terms of stability and plasticity
like as I said it's not like a it's not
exactly a contest uh they're um they're
both important both need to be
considered and they're deeply
interrelated so Colin describes them as
being in a state of something like
Dynamic tension like if you're
insufficiently uh plastic and then
flexible you're not going to stay stable
for long in a changing world uh but if
you don't have a stable base to move
from uh it's going to be hard to be
plastic and reconfigure yourself in a
sustainable way either however you can
also see someone being over um overly
rigid and excessive stability in a way
that undermines their plasticity or
overly flexible in a way that basically
is destabilizing so a dynamic tension
but involving synergies also and I think
in terms of the structure of personality
and well-being this is what we need to
keep in mind that both are needed
stability and plasticity and this is uh
also just within um
it's actually what this was inspired I
think of in Collins thinking to consider
these metatrades this way uh from
machine learning I think actually
reading grossberg and stability
plasticity trade-offs and that's why he
interpreted these meta traits in those
terms uh so I guess one more thing is uh
um
there's a petersonian backstory here
they don't know if I want to get into
but we can discuss it later if there's
interest so
yeah back to Arthur
that was great thanks Adam
yeah very very helpful context which
should hopefully make uh this slide here
much more clear to everyone
um
so given these kind of like two meta
traits uh stability and plasticity which
as Adam you know beautifully described
her in this kind of like Dynamic tension
with one another
um
we can kind of go back to these two
optimization Landscapes and these
machine learning Concepts that I
discussed earlier and kind of try to
understand how these things might all
relate and ultimately you know relate to
psychopathology
so I had hinted before that they're
um
were these kind of two types of
canalization we might say one being
overfitting and another being plasticity
loss and we can interpret these as kind
of like being extremes uh that kind of
like analyzed end of uh how these two
optimization Landscapes might manifest
so in the type a in-print landscape this
looks like overfitting on one end
heavy canalization and underfitting on
the other end in machine learning
context right so overfitting being uh
having very strong rigid beliefs that
are in a particular environmental
context adaptive that are very unlikely
to be adopted in any other context
underfitting being having a set of
beliefs which are not adapted to the
current context and also unlikely to be
adapted to any other context awesome as
far as stability is concerned I I think
we can understand stability this
metatrader is kind of representing the
balance of these two things right you
have high stability when you are an
either
um overfits to a particular contact
store underfit
um so this means you're well fit to this
context that you're right now and you're
also likely the wealth that's other
future context
um I think this is also in complexity
science sometimes described as meta
stability right
um so you're in a stable Point that'll
also likely be able to take you to other
stable points in the future
and this kind of like ability to stay
stable over time is then uh stability
metatrade
we uh can then look at the type B the
learning landscape where the kind of
extreme version of canalization is this
plasticity loss where it's very
difficult to adapt to new contacts
um
the inverse of this is then catastrophic
forgetting where the problem is not one
of adapted to new context the problem is
one of meaningfully retaining adaptive
strategies and beliefs from previous
contexts
um
and so obviously you know neither of
these are desirable
um
what is desirable is some kind of
balance between these two right where
one is able to adapt just enough to new
contacts without being uh
without forgetting previously learned
things
but here the relationship uh to the
metatrade of plasticity is a bit
different than stability right so as it
is being represented on this crop
um you know the more plastic you are
basically the less analyzed you are in
this space the more easy it is to move
around
um but actually extreme versions of this
end up manifesting is catastrophic
forgetting police in the machine
learning context
um and I think this in particular has
relevance for
um
psych pathology and relevance for this
idea maybe complicates this idea right
that uh
psychedelic therapy
is uh in and of itself likely to always
lead to positive outcomes
okay and we can attempt to understand
this by uh making an effort at trying to
map or understand
um various forms of Psychopathology in
the context of these two different
learning Landscapes
um and so before I get into this too
much I think it's important to say that
um this is very much a kind of like
preliminary and provisional attempt at
making sense of these things
um I hope that this is kind of the start
of a
a much more fleshed dialogue looking at
how we can kind of understand
Psychopathology with respect to machine
learning Concepts
um but I think this at least gives like
a good starting point for maybe trying
to understand where and why
um psychedelic therapy is useful isn't
useful
um
which is a bit more nuanced than the
simple idea of like Psychopathology
means canalization and psychedelic
therapy means reducing canalization
right
okay so let's uh try to make sense of
this a little bit
though for the kind of classic set of
Psychopathology is for which there has
been a lot of great research done with
psychedelic therapy and a lot of clear
benefit has been seen
um I think you we can kind of class
these within this upper left-hand corner
here where these are disorders of both
overfitting which means in the moment
over the strong beliefs get represented
you know these are strong attractor
points in the neural activation
landscape
um and
uh plasticity Loft in the type B
landscape which means that not only is a
certain kind of Dynamics instantiated
right which make for example in the case
of the major depressive disorder
extremely negative self-evaluations very
common but it's the case that even given
the correct changes in environmental
context even in the you know even given
in the case of you know psychedelic
system therapy a lot of the work with
major depressive disorders being done
with treatment resistant depression
right and what is treatment resistant
depression but uh a kind of a set of
beliefs a set of neural activity
patterns which are
resistant to adaptation to new
environmental contexts being you know
whatever sort of psychotherapy or
previous drug was used
so this is a high plasticity loss
however fitting right
I think we can then uh
and these are you know kind of
unfortunately you know for psychedelic
therapy and I think maybe for psychiatry
in general these are all very very
common and very very costly uh
psychopathologies right so if it is the
case in psychedelic therapy can treat
these effectively that's fantastic
um
but I think we can maybe look at a more
complicated you know if we start to
expand to other psychopathologies
um this story becomes a little bit more
complicated right
um so let's look we can look at the
bottom left-hand corner here where we
have cases of in the inference landscape
still overfitting but um
in the learning landscape something else
happening a form of catastrophic
forgetting or form of kind of drift of
the
um
the belief landscape that's being
instantiated here right so I think two
kind of Representative
um pathologies here are typically
referred to as some form of bipolar
disorder or some form of borderline
personality disorder right so in both of
these cases in the moment to moment
uh neural activity as it unfolds there
are very strong sets of beliefs being
instantiated at any given time and these
are very difficult to change right
um but
the key differentiating Point here being
that over longer time scales over the
time scales of days or weeks
um the kinds of beliefs that are
instantiated change quite a lot right so
someone who's bipolar if they're in a
manic episode or in a depressive episode
the nature of the belief Landscaping
instantiated is very different
um for borderline individuals from a
daily or weekly basis the nature of
one's beliefs about the people that were
close to them can change very rapidly
um very extremely very in certain cases
and so here the
um
benefit of psychedelic therapy uh is a
bit more mixed where there is likely the
case that to the extent to which the uh
kind of overt type A beliefs can be
updated and changed to be more positive
be hopefully more relaxed
um that's positive but to the extent to
which plasticity may be being increased
when it's not actually needed when
there's not actually like a meaningful
therapeutic benefit to that
um it's a bit questionable I think you
know there's clear
borderline or rather bipolar for example
is often individuals with bipolar are
often excluded from psychedelic files
um
under the assumption for example that
psychedelics may trigger a manic episode
or may trigger psychosis
um and I think that is a valid concern
um so on kind of that topic we can then
this bottom right hand corner would be
cases of both underfooting and
catastrophic forgetting with I think
schizophrenia being kind of like the
most clear manifestation of this
um
and here
um you know there's very little work
currently looking at trying to treat uh
schizophrenia with psychedelic therapy I
think for
pretty good reasons
um
though I would say
to the extent to which there are
secondary uh manifestations secondary
issues like depression anxiety that
people with schizophrenia might have you
know these actually may be treatable
um with some form of psychedelic therapy
and then lastly this upper right hand
corner here
uh would correspond to underfitting in
the type a landscape along with
plasticity laws so I think a good
example of this is something like ADHD
um where there are not very uh
particular strong beliefs that are being
instantiated at any given time
um
but it's difficult to change these side
of beliefs nonetheless
um I think here there's a case uh where
it's not totally clear on how the
benefit will actually play out
um
in both of these cases I you know I've
heard interesting work around like micro
dosing maybe of issue interest
um
I think yeah more research has to be
done to be seen right and then what
would micro dosing be doing right micro
dosing would be like very slowly uh kind
of like
decreasing plasticity loss just a little
bit
um potentially also decreasing
underfitting right
as Adam had kind of suggested in the
office model
and here we have just kind of like a
brief overview of more or less
everything I've described about how
these two Landscapes are different
um I think most of these things I've
said before pretty clearly right so the
type a landscape
it corresponds to the neural activity
pattern this is the hidden state of the
RNN over canalization is going to be
stereotyped mental circuits very
strongly held beliefs under canalization
is going to be these inconsistently
deployed circuits
um
it looks like uh overfitting in the
canalized case underfitting in the
non-catalyzed space
going to correspond to stability to
metatrate
um I hadn't discussed this before but
um I think there's a relationship
between cognitive flexibility and this
inference landscape
psychedelics are mainly going to have
faculty uh work at the acute level care
and this is by directly exciting the
neurons or inducing forms of how to be
in plasticity and the outcome is going
to be a mixture of relaxation and
strengthening of the kind that Adam
described in the the Albus case the type
B landscape then is working on the
synaptic weights and these are the
actual Network parameters in our RNN
model over canalization is this
inability to learn or adapt over time
under canalization is the inability to
retain information right and those
correspond to plasticity loss and
catastrophic forgetting
this also is kind of the traditional
plasticity not a trait
um which I think corresponds to this
more uh this longer term
constructive psychological flexibility
um the effects are going to mainly be
mainly to post acutely with psychedelics
and these are the more Downstream
metaplastic effects um the
psychoplastogenic effects
um and I think on the whole the outcome
the effect here is a relaxation of
catalyzation
and uh yeah these are just the
references so those those are the slides
I have that's kind of the overview of
the deep canals model
um I think now I'll turn it over to Mike
who um who's going to share some
thoughts both about this work and some
of his own work and kind of this uh
approach to understanding psychedelics
more broadly
uh great uh yeah thank you for the that
overview that was great
um so I guess uh I'm just in general
very very optimistic about this corner
of uh of Neuroscience that uh there are
these very intuitive models uh that are
very sort of clinically significant and
uh
and I also think
you know there there is a lot of
responsibility to sort of get things
right here uh as well because as I
remembered
so uh yeah I I have just a few comments
um and uh for the for the viewers uh I
I'm not speaking uh for for Arthur and
Adam um I'm just grateful for uh the
invitation to join the discussion
uh so I wanted to to know uh quickly
three research teams dealing with
uh
the implementation of this class of
model uh so just broadly kind of
pointing at uh both deep canals and uh
andrewbis uh and uh and Albus
um so um
in 2018 I wrote neural annealing and
that was sort of uh developing the
canalization frame within the context of
energy buildup in the eigen modes of a
system
um so you have the the nice
annealing metaphor uh you have a
temperature parameter and entropic
disintegration uh
uh Robin character said a a beautiful
paper on that um uh potential brain
and uh then you you sort of have a post
uh heating result uh where the
microstructure of your system
uh is sort of a result of the
uh sort of how hot and how long the the
heating was so
it's it's an alternative take on belief
relaxation
and I do think that like there are some
pluses in terms of sort of explicitly
making the annealing metaphor
um and uh
uh I think that's uh like two things
that I'd point out uh one top-down
models or top-down predictive models as
energy sinks
um and eigen modes as the places where
energy can build up for almost sort of
hide from top-down models
um so you get this uh this phenomenon of
semantically neutral energy or
semantically illegible energy you can
say uh which is sort of kind of how
uh perhaps uh psychedelics music and
rotation all sort of allow energy but
um they're the energy that they
contribute to the system can evade the
top-down models
um and uh yeah just to note one item
that I'm looking at now is what is
um
deep canals has the inference landscape
versus learning landscape distinction
and how would one sort of build that
distinction within the neural annealing
framework and uh this one one metaphor
that I'm I'm considering is the self as
sort of a magnet uh to sort of
uh apply a constraint a uniform focusing
constraint on the system as it uh as
it's cooling
um the second uh item that I I want to
mention that so I have this piece autism
as a disorder of dimensionality
and uh this brings in the concept of
network density uh that it may very well
be that uh
people on the Spectrum have literally
more neurons and or more synapses and
there's this
great Michelangelo Michelangelo quote I
saw the angel in the stone and I set him
free
um and sort of the thicker networks you
have the more Stone you have to work
with but you actually have to do the
work
um so
uh you you sort of have to have to do
sort of well
normally you sort of inherit these
highly pre-trained optimized circuits
almost like Asics application specific
integrated circuit
um and then uh
this is kind of more uh an untrained
Network and you have to turn it yourself
um and uh within the Deep canals
framework this would show up as both
underfitting and a higher capacity for
plasticity
uh
so I think that's uh that's gonna be a
an interesting thread
um
finally uh so I just posted that last
week principles of vessel computation
and as an implementation level account
of active inference
and this is a big rabbit hole um I I
don't think we have time to to go down
today uh but I just comment that I
really like the way deep canals
explicitly splits out the learning
landscape and the inference landscape
that uh I think that making this
distinction is increasingly going to
make sense
uh back to back Arthur
yeah yeah awesome well thank you all for
the presentations Arthur and Adam feel
free to to pick up where Michael left
off or I can bring in some questions
from the chat or from what I've written
down
yeah
all right just uh yeah
just a quick comment um I do think that
uh in in the Deep canals framework it's
going to be interesting to sort of look
into
uh metabolic demands uh and like sort of
different
uh like
metabolic disorders are are pretty hot
in brain science right now and I do
think that uh it'll be interesting to to
look at sort of
what the metabolic profile is in terms
of each of the four items of a quadrant
um
if one quadrant or another quadrant is
particularly associated with uh
um more metabolic demands in the system
Arthur yeah
yeah that's fascinating I was I'm
actually I'd love to kind of hear a
little bit more about this comment you
made about the cell
as a magnet that's applying these
constraints
oh yeah so
there's a
the like psychedelics the the effects
are not
or sort of the
you sort of get pulled back into
position after
some time
and uh
you know I can't say that this is a full
full Theory uh at this point but um
in the Neuroscience meditation
2018 I talked about um the self as
kind of the
the god of the gaps in terms of aligning
different scales of uh
like you you have circuits which kind of
pull in different ways and you have the
mesoscale systems Which pull in
different ways and you have the the
overall brainwise systems that pull in
different ways and kind of the self is
sort of the thing that I'll try is to
make everything work together
um
and an alternate frame would be sort of
this self is just kind of this
slow gravity toward disalignment
uh yeah um I don't have anything
particularly uh more to share
that's it yeah no that's interesting
well to combine the heating up and the
magnetism different metals and
connections there to Alchemy and
everything different Metals when heated
up and cooled down in specific ways
change their magnetic profile so of
course this is all just concordances but
they're very interesting and then also
to the um the metabolic angle
that reminded me of the um the trilogy
by Dale pendell with uh pharmacist and
and the other two books where treated
alongside traditional psychoactives we
could say like caffeine and nicotine and
some of the other substances that were
mentioned here also there's
tea sugar and these are treated as
psychedelic or at least as uh in the
same
Pantheon of neurocognitive modifying in
the sense that the Destinies of
individuals and of of Empires
ride on
the uh sense making and decision making
influence of sugar for example
so it definitely broadens our
perspective to include the the so-called
classical
molecules like LSD but also maybe we
could think more broadly about
antioxidants or about different lipids
or about different metabolic
um
connections
Michael pollan's uh recent book this is
your mind on Plants I think like it kind
of has that what you're saying in mind
because like it includes caffeine
um not like introduced as a psychedelic
but just disgust among uh also
psychedelics I think their memory
focuses on masculine but
um just it is a different way of being
in the world uh potentially radically
different like if caffeine is in your
life where it is not
um
it's a different life world
and different extended niche
um I'll go to a question in the live
chat so anyone can can give a thought so
Matt asks
is there any way how to approach the
individual reactions to psychedelics in
terms of positive or negative results of
treatment using the ideas of deep canals
so how can we approach predictions and
explanations at the individual scale
with what you're sharing today
one thing for wow
this is kind of like a meta comment but
like if we're actually
going to do
um computational Psychiatry and we
actually are going to and precision
medicine so look at the goal being to
create models of sufficient detail that
they could actually guide our practice
and guide our practice in a way where we
know for an individual what they might
need in any given context so Precision
medicine with respect to like standard
antidepressants
um you know people sometimes will go for
a long time before they find ones that
work and sometimes things are made worse
and they might deal with antidepressant
withdrawal as they're looking for the
right one and if they're in a state of
acute distress that could be um
a hard lot and so like if you can help
to speed up that process of finding what
works uh the ability to and what might
hurt also to avoid that I mean the
ability to help people's immense and so
for that it's um like part of this so
the meta comment is like
um I have to say I'm not convinced that
an active inference uh we're doing the
job
I I think we're not acknowledging our
uncertainty and I think the models are
underspecified with respect to the
complexity of the effects we would
expect on different scales and in
characterizing the systems
and we need to be more patient and
modest
but what we don't know before we go on
rushing in headlong into telling the
rest of Psychiatry how they should
comport themselves and what models they
should use uh based on psychedelic
science and plausible models hopeful
models but very early days and with the
reality being complex in the ways we're
seeing here like this was not an easy
set of lectures you know or a set of
talks like what we're going through this
is like and yeah if we're actually going
to be able to handle these powerful
medicines responsibly we got to go into
the weeds and so anyway so the one more
meta comment was like I think I saw like
someone say oh how can something like
help everything you're like yeah it's
almost I don't know if this is right
it's almost like a violation of like no
free lunch theorems or something it's
like how could something just be good
across the board without you know
something is off you've calculated wrong
somewhere
um you had to pay the price either in
like some trade-off that wasn't
acknowledged or
um but that being said there are some
things which are generally good for a
lot of things like being more flexible
or like if if you can get something like
meta stability like like I said there's
almost like I'm I'm I think I'm a church
member of the the or I'm a faithful
member of the Church of criticality uh I
think Mark Miller might have uh
indoctrinated me with like Optimal grips
but basically like the ability to have
like an optimal grip on existence in
your soul not too tight not too loose
and being able to move around and be
like flexible in itinerant like
something kind of like mindfulness is
just like Sriracha for the soul it's
good for everything almost you just need
to put on this put on that makes it
better I I I I buy that there might be
some things that are good across the
board but I wouldn't call though
uh psychedelics necessarily
um putting you in this like state of
optimal criticality or anything it's
like in general like the rhetoric I'm
uncomfortable with of saying
psychedelics do X I would prefer to say
like
um which psychedel like psychedelics
tend to do X but just a little more
qualifier like not weasel words but just
like a little bit more like uh
this psychedelic might do X in this
context with this dose and this sentence
setting but that being said there do
also those seem to be across the board
um broads um sweeping not super but
overarching statements that we can make
that Express a lot with a little and so
like I don't want to be so much of like
a splitter and like a a a prickly person
finding all the details that like these
powerful things we can basically give to
people to guide like our research I got
I don't want to leave that on table
either so yeah so I guess um that's a
bunch of metal level commentary that did
not address the thing so
I did that too so that's very helpful I
think to have all that context
um with respect to the question itself I
would
um maybe offer this which might be
helpful which is you know I think
you mentioned it Adam and it's very
frequently mentioned this idea of satin
setting right as being like heavily
predictive of the quality of the acute
psychedelic experience and often also to
some extent the quality of the
post-acute experience
um and I think we can understand this in
the Deep canals model quite quite
straightforwardly
um
so I'll just
quickly pull back up one of these slides
here
um
yeah right so
what is satin setting so
um set is mindset which would basically
be some combination of the current uh
your current position in the synaptic
weight landscape and the current state
of your neural activation landscape
right so your place in both Landscapes
is your mindset and uh the setting is
the what is generating this input right
what is generating the X into the
network and that's you know some
complicated function of the environment
right
um and then we can understand right the
evolution of movement through the
inference landscape during the acute
effects of the drug as then kind of like
vary directly and straightforwardly
being a function of these two things
right
um because both of these these things
are are basically what's affecting how
this landscape evolves over time and how
you move through the landscape
um and so you know with this in mind I
guess we can then start to characterize
and think about like okay well what
kinds of uh you know we can maybe be a
little bit more mechanistic about like
how does input
from the environment the setting
actually
given you know that we relatively fix
the actual synaptic one of the way
landscape how is that changing the
Dynamics over time or the other way
around right like how our uh is fixing
the input
the environmental context relatively
stable
um and looking at individuals who are at
different fixed points at different
points of time I'm going to change the
Dynamics but yeah the event right and I
think given that this is a highly
stochastic process given that these
dynamics of Albus are are at play right
where like certain beliefs are being
strengthened other beliefs are being
relaxed
um
I think at least having this hold on
okay well set and setting is really
important and it's important because
like these are explicitly conditioning
the way in which
uh both the landscape the inference
landscape is shaped and how you move
around it and how it's being you know
dynamically perturbed
um yeah hopefully that answers a little
bit the question
nice uh
I just want to jump in there just
thinking about
um biomarkers
that uh
I mean if if we're looking for something
that's of high clinical specificity
uh we want to sort of be able to measure
what's
what's going on uh at a very careful in
a very careful way so like first of all
what is temperature parameter uh you
know we we talk about okay psychedelics
increase the temperature parameters but
um like how high and do do different
substances and dosages uh sort of differ
in interesting ways probably yes
uh and then also sort of measuring
temperature parameter measuring the
temperature parameter in different parts
of the body so you might have a
different uh temperature
like not the real temperature but uh
kind of computational like entropic
concentration uh in different parts of
your body
um and also
um the plasticity status in different
networks throughout your body
so
I guess I
I see a big
Frontier here uh as thinking some doing
some careful thinking around
um biomarkers and proxies and inferring
these these sort of things that we we
are talking about as
core and I think they are core and we
should be able to find a good uh good
marks
yeah that's
totally correct and yeah I just want to
like repeat it for my own occasion right
which is it like yeah these two things
which I think were maybe one was is I
think already a core part of the deep
Penance work right which is that I was
showing these single images of these toy
optimization Landscapes but of course
um
the human being the nervous system right
uh has multiple many of these Landscapes
hierarchically organized right
um and they influence each other in a
complicated way
um
and
the kind of like
yeah the project for it is to understand
where these Landscapes are what they
look like and how we can find biomarkers
to them yeah and again you know if he's
two kinds of characterizations are true
um this overfitting underfitting
plasticity loss and uh catastrophic
forgetting then it would
it's a very meaningful project to be
able to you know quantify that
objectively somehow an individual and
that's when you can start to get to this
point that Adam was talking about like
Precision medicine and understanding
like okay well actually it turns out
right like these networks are catalyzed
in this kind of way and because of that
we can say with much more certainty that
this kind of you know psychedelic
intervention is going to likely be
helpful
so
I'm wondering I don't know if this like
potentially brings in some of the work
with like um uh
vascular and neuroviscellular uh
neurovascular and visceral integration
that you're doing but like
so there's like a sense in like the free
energy principle where the overall
phenotype
and an extended phenotype in terms of
its cut its constructing and coupling
with and constructing its Eco Niche
there's
um it's success and manifesting this
phenotype
um it's there's one for energy function
for this overall effort as a kind of
prediction that's enacted through the
Dynamics but you could also like break
it down in terms of like subsystems with
like local gradients and like local auto
poetic processes that are in like
they're brought together into an overall
system hopefully with synergies
um but and they have to be to be in an
organism and an agent we call this like
I think
to the extent it has thickness it's
coming together but I guess so you could
I guess think of maybe like a energy
landscape you know something like uh
let's just say like right now in this
moment like my uh explicitly felt
beliefs but my my body also might have a
different opinion different parts of it
and it in terms of like what it's
implicitly optimizing it's revealed
preference from its in action that may
or may not correspond to how I feel
about it I might not even it might be
difference of opinion I might even be
tuning in I might be ignoring it because
I don't want to and so it's kind of like
the score kept by the body might have
its own
um uh be describable as its own like
information geometry which is being
tracked to degrees and is in different
degrees of uh alignment with
um different ones at different levels of
a control hierarchy so plausible right
yeah absolutely I I think so um yeah uh
and like I I think of I think the body
is sort of um uh a parliament of
different uh networks and uh
you know alignment is the scarce
resource coordination is always a
scarcity resource and uh like how does
the body keep alignment and when does it
go wrong too and I guess I I see this as
sort of
um I mean harmonically mediated each
part of the body has some choice of what
else in the body to listen to
and depending on the particular sort of
location in the information topology
uh different parts of the body have
different carrots and sticks by which to
try to control other parts of the body
uh so if if your stomach is very unhappy
uh it's going to start rambling and then
it's uh it'll it'll let the body know
okay I need some food like I really
seriously need some food
um and then yeah the rest of the body
they can sort of turn away from it uh
and then it'll just get louder and then
you have to turn it away from it more a
little bit louder and that's a of course
a negative Dynamic if it gets What It
Wants maybe it's sort of
gives a very harmonious hum uh and uh
and sort of tries to give give Carriage
the rest of the body so yeah I just uh
there's an ecosystem there
I'll go to another question in the live
chat so Bert asks
what do you think of the average of
solving within a generative hierarchy
and the impact of temporary openness
moving it upwards
and then I asked to clarify what do you
mean the average of solving and Bert
wrote where predictions meet incoming
signals like discussed in Rebus where
top down predictions are softened in
precision and dust and thus solved for
oh
I think Arthur will be able to get into
the details of that
um
better than I would but the uh one thing
I'm
wondering there is um
sometimes like like in like again I love
the entropic brain uh but sometimes I
wonder in terms of like the connections
whether I don't so how we're having more
or less entropy and whether that matters
the how so for instance like you can
think of like a free energy landscape
that's been flattened or you can think
of one where like you're better able and
you have like more like energy for like
this uh you know the manifold activity
is better of like climbing up or down
the the Peaks that are there for the
more enduring belief landscape so it's
like in the moment it could be that
um uh
my previous way of thinking is
unavailable to me and I no longer
believe those things at any level
um or I I can uh support more novel
inferences that I wouldn't otherwise I
can kind of move into an area of Mind
space that would otherwise be difficult
potentially because
of of greater energy into the system
greater thorough put
nice
yeah so as I as I think I understand the
question right it's basically asking
about trying to optimize for this free
energy
um
variable and in the con the context of
deep canals right like this is the loss
function that's driving the optimization
of the the learning landscape the
synaptic great landscape right but like
the entire connectivity structure of the
nervous system is like trying to get to
this point of like low-free energy and I
think there's lots of uh there's you
know for any given individual in a given
environment assuming the environment is
relatively fixed right there's like an
optimal
um there's a global optimal and it's
very likely that the individual is in
some local Optima
um that is maybe close to it maybe far
from it
um
but that's just inherently you know
um what was you know within the context
of the active entrance that's what we're
assuming that the nervous system is
doing is is doing this great into some
in the space and openness then is going
to
uh correspond to this plasticity
metatrade or be one of the components of
it and it is in the Deep canals model
then going to correspond to an ability
to move around this optimization
landscape more easily right it's going
to be a flattening of a landscape or
more precisely I guess a student of the
landscape
um such that it's less likely that
the individual the nervous system will
get stuck in these local Optimum
so maybe it won't mean that the
individual will arrive at the global
Optimum I think it's difficult to say
what that even you know might be or
however our individuals might get to
such a place at all but I think it is
likely that the individual will be will
be more likely to find a more
uh more Global Optimum and more easily
move from one uh option to another right
and I think that's kind of what this
this openness is corresponding to
um
yeah
it's okay
oh I
so in in neural kneeling I uh I
mentioned the
uh the idea of psychedelic extrapolating
volition kind of a play on uh coherent
extrapolated position from uh from the
AI safety crowd and it's this sort of
sense that um
if temporarily you have more control
over sort of low level shaping of of
your
your condition your emotion
um and you know maybe sort of based on
this this attractor that we call the
South uh or you know I I guess like
based on what is a good question
um then
what are good signs that you should be
trusted with that power or you should
trust yourself with that power rather
and what are what are telltale signs
that you shouldn't trust yourself with
that power and um you know I I don't
have an answer but I think it's an
interesting question
yes I am normal and can be trusted with
the key to the doors of perception let
me in exactly
um I have a short question
where is action in this model
so
um
imagine many places Arthur will get into
that but for
um what I was thinking with
um Albus is that actually the 5-ht2a
system
um
I I talk about two regimes potentially
um one is more towards
um overt in action and modifying the
world and strength and beliefs
potentially of that variety and the
other might be more of um adapting to
the world uh it's so uh Robin has a a
really excellent paper called The Tale
of Two receptors where he talks about
5hc two five ht1a receptors the ones
that antidepressants tend to act on
um because they tend to reduce this
excitatory signaling
um talk about them as a kind of passive
coping and so this would correspond and
there's some machine learning models of
this by Diane and colleagues of like
where they talk about opponency between
dopamine serotonin and they're focusing
on the 1A as a kind of like patients
promoting parameter keeping you from
like confidently charging into your
policy so that would tend to
inhibit I guess patterns of
um either Overton action or potentially
even some kinds of um uh mental
simulation too if it's like you could
maybe even think of like even if you're
not overtly inactive enacting something
externally uh there might be more or
less uh Brave type styles of thoughts
that you might be willing to entertain
going
um
going places you might not otherwise
um be willing to go and being able to
handle the swings and expected free
energy that might happen as you try to
pursue a given path of policies
so but the idea would be that
um there might be something more like a
micro dosing Mesa dosing regime which
might be more of what initially sculpted
the five hd2a system which evolved with
the gene duplication event around the
time of uh the Cambrian explosion with
the Advent of jawed fishes I'm
personally interpreting this as having
the significance of
um evolving the context of Predator prey
arms races I suspect I could be wrong
but that basically it's
um locally trying to strengthen patterns
of policy pursuit to pursue particular
goals in a given context and this to
come back to what was I think earlier
without work by Robin of like a kind of
active coping but it seems with Rebus
um there's almost like um a
not that kind of story
um and that it's more your adjusting to
the world and actually if under a very
alter say you are overtly enacting
that's actually kind of a dangerous
thing I don't know how much to make of
this at the
um 582 receptors are less expressed on
like motor cortex I don't think we know
enough to make too much of it but it's
like some dreams you might not want to
act out as they're happening but they
still might powerfully impact you
so um I'm currently actually wondering
whether this other Rebus like regime
might have been specifically sculpted in
the context of
um bonding and actually opening the self
to include others and that might have
been some of the primary selective
pressures I don't know how to think of
that in terms of an action
um but uh and one more detail that might
kind of like uh not sure what to make of
it the kind of
goes through both of those
excuse the phone uh would be
um anthropologically I believe like
psychedelics are oftentimes used in ways
that would be both like creating a kind
of group solidarity and might be used in
the context of
um pursuing goals together in the world
so for instance like a hunting party
they might all do psychedelics together
or something that looks a lot like
breath work before uh going out maybe
you know going to war so that's a very
different type that kind of includes
both a relaxation of the normal
boundaries of the self and the kind of
like uh gearing you up for pursuing
goals in the world so but you know
there's got to be another story of like
like those Arthur's expertise is machine
learning and so it's like uh these you
want these systems to act intelligently
and not act in other times and so
basically now we're in the language of
policies and when you deploy them and
how and yes so
complicated
yeah I would say that action manifests
itself in a few different places it's
trying to mention it here yeah I think
it's really important obviously I mean I
think what the kind of like most
implicit place where it exists right is
that
um these belief Landscapes are being
instantiated ultimately for the sake of
adaptive Behavior adaptive Behavior
adaptive action right in some sort of
environmental context and that's the
kind of like framework deep learning
framework that we're using or like the
artificial agent framework right is that
like the assumption is that the system
is
supporting some sort of agent that's
embodied in some sort of environment
which is you know changing over time
um such that it can either be adaptive
or not adaptive I think then the
question of how action actually plays
into the evolution of these belief
Landscapes you know during psychedelics
or not
um
you know acting is a acting in the world
is a very clear way to
modify one's setting right so action is
a way of modifying the function that's
providing the sensory input into the
system which is going to evolve change
how the activity patterns are evolving
over time right which is going to affect
the acute quality of the trip
um it affects how beliefs are either
being strengthened or relaxed
um and I think you know it's it's
already clear that
there's a kind of whole
um
that of like folk psychology right
that's been built around like what is or
is a good way to
uh cultivate
a helpful setting and that of course all
is a function of action in the world I
think that there's also
um this kind of more subtler form of
action which is how one thinks Holland
deploys attention right essentially
during this experience and I think this
deployment of attention has a huge
effect on whether there end up being
Rebus or cbis like effects right so
whether one allows oneself to go down
certain thought rabbit holes whether one
allows oneself to get kind of stuck in
certain kinds of thought patterns
um
I think this form of mental action
yeah has a very big Downstream effect
um
and I think a lot of I'd love to see
much more work on this I think it's very
important I think it's kind of essential
um and I think this is kind of one of
the most interesting things about these
psychedelic
experiences is that
in some sense like the most extreme
revised model and the most extreme uh
Phoebus model
could be true for two different
individuals right someone could say you
know I went to hell and I was there for
eight hours straight or
um
or say you know I had a completely
selfless experience I like let go of all
beliefs and experience you know nothing
for eight hours straight it was great
right and like um clearly those involve
like two very different neural regimes
and I think the nature and you know
obviously given that they involve the
same drug and they involve not such a
different setting it's obvious that they
um something very important to do with
how attention is deployed during this
experience yeah
yeah just I do think that this Frame of
attention I mean attention is so
important for for everything and I do
think that there's something interesting
kind of digging into the the attention
and Elvis uh
framework that um
yeah I'm really curious to see how
that'll that'll develop I I would also
say that um
in terms of active inference and action
there is a cost to holding an attention
um and then you once you know you
discharge your intention you can release
that cost
um so I I guess I would have to think
about how to apply that to the Canal's
framework
um Fred Barrett um I don't know if he's
published it yet
but this is kind of like a follow-up to
a a cloud Sterling Central model that
Arthur alluded to uh um is emphasizing
basically um a lack of executive control
and placing that is Central to the
Psychedelic experience like it's not
controlling your mental action and
directed ways as much and then trying to
come from more of the um types of
cognition and phenomenology sort of
psychedelics based on just releasing of
uh the normal more agentic modes of
policy selection around attention as
mental action although he uh not using
active inference speak so
yes
you have very interesting Adam you're
um
your introduction there of of course
attention as covert action
which was echoed by by Arthur and
Michael both of you said
it really introduces uh a case where we
can use active inference to find
continuity between what's happening
inside the agent and outside the agent
because on one hand we could kind of
take a belief-oriented frame and we
could say well what's happening inside
the agent are beliefs about things
beliefs about hidden States beliefs
about observations beliefs about policy
so that's kind of a belief-oriented view
where everything is framed it basically
cognitively or we could take a very
action-oriented View and then we could
think about the interface in a more
inactive way and then also even the
realm of where where many active
entities uh dare not tread
in mental action with attention as
covert action and so then we have like a
a total active account
that is mathematically isomorphic with
the total belief-based accounts they're
both just Maps they're not the territory
the territories the person in the room
so all of this is just talking about the
formalism and how we choose to interpret
the formalism in terms of it being more
inferential or it being more active
um and so there's a lot of
ways to go
I guess in our closing
minutes I would love to hear
what are the next
moves or what are some areas that you um
would hope that people look into
Michael and then the authors
okay so I know it's
um
I think my my favorite mental move is to
try to drop down on my level of
abstraction okay how how is this
implemented um what's what's going on
here and then
I do think that details of
implementation
um are really generative to look into
and like to buy markers and proxies for
you know figuring out how to have
parameterize okay exactly how hot is are
we talking about with this temperature
parameter and so on and in different
parts of the body
um I I have kind of my
my Niche that I'm I'm working on in the
Vaso muscular system uh which is a
rebital but um
yeah I just think that like
I do think that this
like the Deep canals framework
specifically and the canalization
Paradigm in general
um
it's good enough that we should be able
to dig into mechanisms so I'm I'm
looking forward to that
great
Adam
or Arthur the government doesn't so um
or Arthur you can go first feel like it
doesn't matter
okay yeah okay sure
um yeah I mean first I want to Echo this
idea uh I think back to this is very
important this is one of you know the
people we've talked to about
talked with about deep canals this idea
of like well this is great you have
these two axes you know it'd be
wonderful if there was some like
biological correlates you could look for
um I think that's incredibly important
um my background was also in machine
learning uh in deep learning so I'm
currently doing some work around like
simulating some of these things I think
uh especially for these Albus Dynamics
uh
being able to kind of like study under
what circumstances you've got these
different kinds of effects even in kind
of like simple toy models is kind of
important to see how they unfold
um
and then I'm also you know we brought it
up at the end I think it's really
important it's very interesting to me is
that the role of the deployment of
attention in this
um and there's lines of work where
people are trying
you know various researchers are trying
to connect for example meditation to
psychedelic research and kind of certain
people are trying to tell unified
stories about
um
what's going on in the brain when people
meditate what's going on they're just
psychedelics
um some of them using these active
imprints models
um but I think in all of these cases the
deployment of attention and how the
deployment of tension changes over time
is kind of a key aspect of this
um and it's not as it's not as present
in the Deep canals model right now but I
think
any any really robust future kind of
like model or these things is going to
happen talk about attention quite a bit
um I guess next steps would be um seeing
how the review process goes but also
um
I guess helping Arthur to establish a
field of psychedelic machine learning
psychedelic inspired machine learning
where we use we try to make systems more
flexible and capable better they can
handle edge cases better imagine better
in terms of real-time policy selection
learn in ways that uh not too much not
too little
and then maybe you know so that's useful
potentially earlier like you have a
driverless vehicle do I change lanes or
don't I you send it back to the Tesla
Dojo what do you want to learn what do
you not wanted to learn
um but then down the line
um
before we even get there you know as
you're going into this you could see the
capacity for like a rich bi-directional
flow between machine learning and
psychedelic inspired machine learning so
it's like you get a bunch of machine
Learners together and a bunch of people
who know a lot about the cognitive
science and biology and maybe
phenomenology of psychedelics
and in addition to designing better
machine Learning Systems they could
probably tell you more about how
psychedelics act and so you can have
this kind of virtuous cycle between
the biology and the field
but you keep going with that
um I guess before we get there we'll
keep going but before we get there
um
very interested in the implications for
Best Practices so for instance like
there might be like when so oftentimes
you might want semantically neutral
energy to kind of get them you're
turning up the heat you're just maybe at
first breaking up you know like home
defenses but the usual structure but
then the question is at what point do
you try to direct the canalization
process do you wait till after or maybe
when the when the metal is hot is that a
really good time to do it and so these
are the kinds and maybe there's no one
single question this might depend on the
substance the set the setting the dose
the person is so getting Clarity on that
could be uh faithful for many people in
terms of
um the outcomes they have and I
specifically what I'm uh gunning for is
I'm on a mission to make uh compassion
meditation uh treatment as usual for uh
all psychedelic Psychotherapy and
preferably All Therapy and so the
question is like if you're in a state of
enhanced imaginative capacity maybe
you're having more ability to tune into
your interceptive system whether you've
just increased the channels or maybe
you're better capable of because maybe
your inflammation went down a bit you
can tune in better because it doesn't
feel it feels better to do so some
combination that might be a really good
opportunity to do certain meditations
that might update you in particular ways
like try to direct the re-annealing
process maybe not just like afterwards
integration but during the session and
so if we could get clarity on something
like
um how to catalyze and recanalyze in the
like annealing schedules like it's going
to be complicated but that's I think
where we need to head and then finally
um for all this I'm very uh
that would be enough but um re-centering
the conversation on psychedelics on
basically meaning and connection would
be enough
but I'm wondering uh down the line when
we talk of alignment
we're talking about our alignment with
our values and maybe the alignments of
machines with our values
and so
does this actually end up going to some
of the conversations that are happening
now about increasingly Advanced Ai and
our relationships to it could there be a
story of canalization and recanalyzation
uh you want some things to hold fast and
you want some things to be more fluid
this might be it's always been a timely
conversation we've always been dealing
with this with us the alignment problem
of us which we often fail but the
alignment problem
that these Technologies were developing
wow well
so many great topics thank you all
I have in closing turn on tune in actin
first serve
thank you
see you all next time